Guide to the Elsie Clark Krug Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Elsie Clark Krug Papers
1909-1985
RG 142
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
(7 boxes)
Detailed correspondence, diaries, photographs, and collected material document the life and work of a young, single woman missionary in China. Elsie Clark Krug was an American Methodist missionary in Foochow from 1912 to 1918. She taught at Hwa Nan College, then in its preliminary stages a mission-supported college for women.
Krug, Elsie Clark, 1888-
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elsie Clark Krug.
Biographical / Historical
1888 Aug 6 Born in Baltimore, Maryland
1905 Graduated from Girls' Latin School
1909 Graduated from Goucher College (then known as Woman's College of Baltimore), Phi Beta Kappa
19xx Received M.A. degree from the University of Chicago Divinity School
1912 Went to Foochow, Fukien Province, China under auspices of Methodist Episcopal Church to teach at Hwa Nan College.
1918 Returned home on furlough; married Andrew H. Krug
1921 Daughter, Dorothy, born.
192x Following a separation and later divorce, Elsie Clark Krug owned and ran a gift shop, specializing in imports from China and elsewhere.
1953 Retired
1982 Nov 30 Died
Scope and Contents
This is a small but valuable collection of letters, diaries, and collected material documenting the life, thoughts, and work of a young single woman missionary in China. Elsie Clark (Krug) wrote to her family on a frequent basis throughout her years in China and included detailed description of her activities and surroundings. Elsie Clark figures prominently in Jane Hunter's work The Gospel of Gentility.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1912-1918
II. Diaries, 1912-1914
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1909-1986
IV. Photographs, 1909-1963
V. Collected Material, 1913-1947
Missions -- China; Women missionaries; Krug, Elsie Clark, 1888-; Hua nan nü zi wen li xue yuan (Fuzhou Shi, Fujian Sheng, China)
- Correspondence, 1912-1918; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Letters to/from family, 1912 Nov -1913 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - Extracts of letters, 1913, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letters to/from family, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 9-14)
    - Letters to/from family, 1915 Jan - 1916 Mar (Box 3, Folder 15-21)
    - Letters to/from family, 1916 Mar - 1917 Feb (Box 4, Folder 22-28)
    - Letters to/from family, 1917 Feb - Dec (Box 5, Folder 29-34)
  - General correspondence
    - Jones, Jennie D., 1913 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Krug, Andrew, 1913-1916 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Faithfull-Davies, Margaret, 1917, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Chinese friends and students, 1913-1920, 1948, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Wallace, Ethel, 1948, 1961, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Willis, Katharine, 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Unidentified, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Diaries, 1912-1914; Series II
  - Diaries, 1912, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Diaries, 1914 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1909-1986; Series III
  - Memorabilia, biographical documentation, 1909-1979 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Obituary, interview with daughter, 1982, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Notes for extra-curricular class on the problems of girlhood (at Hwa Nan), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Photographs, 1909-1963,n.d.; Series IV
  - Photos of ECK, colleagues, students, 1909-1963,n.d. (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Photograph album - scenes and people in Foochow and Fukien, 1912-1918, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Scenes in China, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 49)
- Collected Material, 1913-1947; Series V
  - Copies of the Kuliang Register, 1913-1915 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Copies of the Foochow Express, 1913-1916 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Book on Chinese festivals, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous, 1913-1947, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 53-54)
  - Chinese language primers, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 55)